Register of the David Spencer collection
Hoover Institution Archives
David Spencer collection
1971-1995
92022
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.8 linear feet)
Salvadoran military interrogation and other reports, transcripts of interrogations, Salvadoran government press releases, captured guerrilla documents, guerrilla warfare manuals, leaflets, flyers, and photographs relating to guerrilla activities of the Farabundo Martí National Liberation Front in El Salvador and to allegations of human rights abuses in El Salvador. Includes a summary study with selected translations by David Spencer.
Spencer, David, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1974 Received PhD in economics from Texas A&M University
1974-1975 Visiting professor at Michigan State University
1975-1979 Taught at Illinois State University
1975-1986 Taught at Washington State University
1981 Received tenure at Washington State University
1988-1989 Visiting professor at Massachusetts Institute of Technology
1990 Received the Best Article Award from the peer-reviewed academic journal Economic Inquiry
1991 Moved to Brigham Young University and taught as full professor
1996 Published From Vietnam to El Salvador: The Saga of the FMLN Sappers and Other Guerrilla Special Forces in Latin America
1997 Received a Fulbright Scholarship to Vietnam
1998-2001 Chair of Graduate Record Examination Committee
2005 Received the Alcuin Fellowship Award at Brigham Young University
2007-2008 Visiting professor at University of Michigan
Scope and Content of Collection
The David Spencer collection includes Salvadoran press bulletins, military interrogation transcripts, and captured guerrilla manuals and documents relating to guerilla group activities of the Frente Farabundo Martí para la Liberación Nacional (FMLN) during the Salvadoran Civil War. Additional materials include captured correspondence, diaries, memoranda, pamphlets, photographs, battle reports, and a few printed materials pertaining to FMLN activities while at war with the Salvadoran military. There are also two drafts by Spencer on the FMLN Special Forces and the Cold War in Latin America, as well as photographs taking by Spencer while in El Salvador during the Civil War. Note that the majority of the collection is photocopies made by Spencer of materials from the Salvadoran Archives.
Guerrillas--El Salvador.; Frente Farabundo Martí para la Liberación Nacional.; Civil rights--El Salvador.
- Speeches and Writings, 1992
  - FES: The Special Forces of the FMLN, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - The External War: The Argentine Dirty War in Central America, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Research File, 1971-1995
  - General, circa 1980-1990
    - Historia del FMLN, 1989 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - El Proceso de Paz en El Salvador, circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Press bulletins, 1989-1992
    Scope and Contents note
    Published by the Salvadoran government related to events occurring during the Civil War.
    - 1989 (Box-folder 1: 5-7)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 1: 8, 2: 1-2)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 2: 3-6)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980, 1983
    Captured correspondence between FMLN guerrillas and a letter from Archbishop Leonidas Proano of Riobamba, Ecuador to the FMLN.
    - General, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Letter from Proano, Leonidas Archbishop of Riobamba, Ecuador, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Letter to Javier, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Manuals, 1971-1988
    Manuals confiscated from the FMLN covering guerrilla military strategy and tactics, political and policy guidelines, and how to create and run a political party. The manuals originate either from Cuba or the Soviet Union and borrow military and political knowledge from other Cold War conflicts in Vietnam and Latin America.
    - General, 1980s (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Memoranda, 1980-1995
    - General, 1980s (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
    - 1980-1981 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1992-1993 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Microfilm duplicates, circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Pamphlets, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Photographs, 1980-1991
    Photographs taken by Spencer cover over a decade’s worth of history, illustrating the mood and atmosphere during the Salvadoran Civil War. The photographs are of Salvadoran military exercises and graduation ceremonies of the Atlacatl Battalion (an alleged death squad), FMLN guerrilla contraband, and weapons captured by the Salvadoran military. There are also photographs of Salvadoran political and military leaders and other notable figures of the era.
    - Photocopies, circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - 1980-1991 (Box-folder 5: 1-60)
  - Reports, 1978-1992
    - General, 1980s (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6: 3-4)
    - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Transcripts, 1980-1990
    - General, circa 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - 1980-1990 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Interrogations, 1981-1990
      Salvadoran military-transcribed interrogations of captured FMLN guerrillas. The transcripts contain family, academic, and personal information, as well as information relating to FMLN movements, locations, and munition stockpiles.
      - Alvila-Rodriguez, Milton Sifredo, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - Caceres-Galindo, Jose Antonio, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - Castillo-Morales, Juan Jose, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - Diaz-Umana, T. Gilberto, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - Hernandez-Hespinosa, Ricardo de Jesus, 1989 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Hernandez-Portillo, Jose Justiniano, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - Mijango-Flores, Jose Humberto, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - Morales-Galvez, Santos Salome, circa 1980-1990 (Box-folder 7: 8)
      - Rivas-Melendez, Jose Herminio, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - Romero-Tavaver, Jolio Santiago, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 10)
      - Torrez-Richards, Federico Ruben, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 11)
      - Valle-Hernandez, Cesar Alberto, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - Zepeda-Gonzalez, Carlos Rolando, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Printed matter, 1983, 1992
    - General, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      Contains radio bulletins, leaflets, political flyers, and other ephemera. Note that this appears to be original material.
    - Diario Latino, 1992 (Box-folder 7: 15)
      Contains photocopies of four issues of the newspaper Diario Latino.